Guide to the Records of the Office of the President (Dr. James McNaughton Hester) RG.3.0.7
New York University Archives
- Series VI: Finances, 1966-1975 (Boxes 45-50)
  Box 48 contains information on the decision to sell the Heights campus and the response from alumni and students. Initially the University tried to seek an alternative to the sale through appeals legislators and a variety of alternative proposals. When it became obvious that the sale would take place, the material changes to agreements and contracts including a merger agreement between NYU's Engineering and Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn. These plans were vigorously opposed by the students and alumni and there is considerable correspondence about the decision to close the Heights campus in Box 49. Box 49 also contains information and correspondence about the decision to merge the school of engineering with the Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute, a plan that was also strongly opposed by alumni and students.
  Box 50 consists of University memos regarding finances. These memos provide a quick understanding in chronological form of what the administration was trying to do about the financial crisis.
  - Banking, 1972-1973 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Bonds, 1973-1974 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Budget, 1970-1973 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Budget, Five year plan, 1970-1973 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Committee on the Financial Emergency, 1972 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Dean's comments on task force formation, 1972 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, 1966-1970 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, 1971 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, 1972 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, 1972 (Box 45, Folder 10)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, 1972 (Box 45, Folder 11)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, 1973 (Box 45, Folder 12)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, 1974-1975 (Box 45, Folder 13)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, Task Force report, 1969-1973 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Financial Crisis NYU,Faculty response to memo, 1971 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Financial Crisis at NYU, Faculty placement, 1972 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Financial Crisis in Higher Education, 1969-1971 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Financial Crisis in Higher Education, 1971 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Financial Crisis in Higher Education, 1972 (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Financial Crisis in Higher Education, 1972 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Financial Crisis in Higher Education, 1973-1974 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Financial Crisis in Higher Education, 1975 (Box 46, Folder 9)
  - Financial Crisis in Higher Education, 1973-1974 (Box 46, Folder 10)
  - Financial Crisis in Higher Education,Carnegie, 1970-1974 (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Financial Statements, 1972-1974 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Graduate School of Social Work, protests, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - GSSW, letters protesting plan to close, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - GSSW, letters protesting plan to close, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - GSSW, letters protesting plan to close, 1972-1973 (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Hurd comm report on financing Higher Ed in NY, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - Investments, 1972-1973 (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - Investments, 1974-1975 (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - NYU Reports and Statistics, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 11)
  - State Education Department, 1971-1973 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Task Force Report, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Task Force Report, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - University Heights Campus Sale, 1970-1972 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - University Heights Campus Sale, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - University Heights Campus Sale, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - University Heights Campus Sale, 1973 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - University Heights Campus Sale, 1973-1974 (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - University Heights Campus Sale,memos regard., 1972 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - University Heights Legislation, 1971-1972 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Univ. Hgts, letters opposing decision to sell, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Univ Hts, letters supporting decision to sell, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - U Hts: School Eng merger w/ Brooklyn Poly Inst, 1970-1972 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - U Hts: School Eng merger w/ Brooklyn Poly Inst, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - U Hts: School Eng merger w/ Brooklyn Poly Inst, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - U Hts: School Eng merger w/ Brooklyn Poly Inst, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - U Hts: School Eng merger w/ Brooklyn Poly Inst, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - U Hts: School Eng merger w/ Brooklyn Poly Inst, 1972-1973 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - U Hts: School Eng merger w/ Brooklyn Poly Inst, 1973 (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - University Memos, 1969-1971 (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - University Memos, 1972-1975 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Sub Series I: Task Force
    - University Memos, 1972-1975 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Working Papers, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Working Papers, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Materials sent to Committee, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Working Agenda, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Meetings March, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Meetings March-April, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Meetings April, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Meetings April, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 9)
    - Meetings April-May, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Governance, 1951-1975 (Boxes 51-59)
  The governance series consists of 45 linear inches of materials and contains information on the operation of the University and the higher authorities to whom the University was responsible. Box 51 is devoted to correspondence to the Regents Advisory Committee of the NYC Regional Plan for Higher Education. Box 52 contains correspondence with the State University of New York Regents Council for Post Secondary Education in New York City. Box 53 and 54 contain correspondence with the State Education Department and the Board of Trustees. Individual files on Board of Trustee members, which contain correspondence as well as biographical material also begin in Box 54 and continue into Box 55. Most end with a note of condolence to the member's surviving family. Files on the President's councils for such divisions as the College of Public and Business Administration begin in Box 55.
  Boxes 56, 57, and 58 continue with the President's Councils and contain such divisions as the School of Education, Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, and the Graduate School of Social Work. Box 59 contains folders on the administrative officers including the President, the Provost, the Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Science, and the University Senate. There is also a folder on student involvement at the end.
  The several folders on the President concern trips taken by him and do not represent the official function of the office.
  - Governance, 1969-1971 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - University of state of NY Board of Regents, 1971-1974 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Regents Advisory Council-NYC Plan Higher Ed., 1971 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Regents Advisory Council-NYC Plan Higher Ed., 1971 (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - Regents Advisory Council-NYC Plan Higher Ed., 1972 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Regents Advisory Council-NYC Plan Higher Ed., 1972 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Regents Advisory Council-NYC Plan Higher Ed., 1972 (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - Regents Advisory Council-NYC Plan Higher Ed., 1972 (Box 51, Folder 8)
  - Regents Advisory Council-NYC Plan Higher Ed., 1972-1973 (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - SUNY Regents:Coord.Council Post Secondary Ed., 1972 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - SUNY Regents:Coord.Council Post Secondary Ed., 1973 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - SUNY Regents:Coord.Council Post Secondary Ed., 1973 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - SUNY Regents:Coord.Council Post Secondary Ed., 1973 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - SUNY Regents:Coord.Council Post Secondary Ed., 1973 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - SUNY Regents:Coord.Council Post Secondary Ed., 1974 (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - SUNY Regents:Coord.Council Post Secondary Ed., 1974 (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - SUNY Regents:Coord.Council Post Secondary Ed., 1974 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - SUNY, State Education Department, 1968-1972 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - SUNY, State Education Department, 1972-1975 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - SUNY,State Ed Dept,Advisory Council Higher Ed, 1973-1974 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1971-1972 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Audit committee, 1970 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Membership and Honors Committee, 1968 (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Student Services & Aux Bus Operations, 1968 (Box 53, Folder 8)
  - Lists, 1969-1974 (Box 53, Folder 9)
  - G & G, Begrisch, F.W., 1961-1972 (Box 53, Folder 10)
  - Brush, Alvin G., 1956-1965 (Box 53, Folder 11)
  - Ehram, Frederick L., 1955-1973 (Box 53, Folder 12)
  - Emmerich, Fred J., 1953-1972 (Box 53, Folder 13)
  - Ettinger, Richard P., 1952-1956 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Ettinger, Richard P., 1967-1971 (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Ettinger, Richard P. Tax Center, 1964-1965 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Ettinger, Richard P., 1968-1969 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Ettinger, Richard P. Scholars, 1966-1970 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Leidesdorf, Samuel D., 1953-1973 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Madden, James L., 1962-1972 (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - Roasch, John E., 1953-1973 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Sarnoff, David, 1971 (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Simpson, Malcolm, 1952-1967 (Box 54, Folder 10)
  - Sockman, Ralph W., 1952-1971 (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - Valente, Francis L., 1960-1966 (Box 54, Folder 12)
  - Ettinger, Richard P., 1967-1971 (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Van Bomel, Leroy A., 1952-1967 (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Wachenfeld, William A., 1955-1969 (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Whitmarsh, Francis L., 1951-1966 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Councils and Commissions, 1973-1974 (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Councils & Comm-Administrative Mgmt Council, 1970-1975 (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - Councils & Commissions - Presidents Council, 1969-1972 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Councils & Commissions - Graduate Commission, 1973-1974 (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - President's Councils - Center for Int. Study, 1965-1972 (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - School of Business, 1965-1975 (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - College of BPA, 1972 (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - School of Education, 1969-1972 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, 1965 (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - GSAS, 1966-1967 (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - GSAS, 1968 (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - GSAS, 1969-1972 (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - GSAS, 1965-1969 (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - GSAS, 1965-1967 (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Graduate School of Social Work, 1968-1971 (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - Graduate School of Social Work, 1972-1974 (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - Near East & North African Studies, 1968-1976 (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - School of Continuing Education, 1966-1972 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Libraries, 1966-1972 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - School of Continuing Education, 1966-1972 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - School of Continuing Education, 1966-1972 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Libraries, 1966-1972 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - Councils and Commissions Wash Sq Council, 1973-1974 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Graduate Professional Ed., 1973-1975 (Box 57, Folder 7)
  - Arts, School of the, 1966-1967 (Box 57, Folder 8)
  - Dentistry, College of, 1965-1971 (Box 57, Folder 9)
  - Engineering & Science, School of, 1965-1971 (Box 57, Folder 10)
  - Institute of Fine Arts, 1965-1971 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - University College of Arts and Sciences, 1965-1972 (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - Washigton Square College of Arts & Sci., 1965-1966 (Box 58, Folder 3)
  - Joint Meetings, 1967-1968 (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - University Heights Council, 1965-1971 (Box 58, Folder 5)
  - Commission on Effective Use of Resources, 1969-1971 (Box 58, Folder 6)
  - Commission on Undergraduate Education, 1970-1971 (Box 58, Folder 7)
  - Commission of University Purposes (Box 57, Folder 8)
  - Commission on Safety, 1970 (Box 58, Folder 9)
  - Administrative Offices, 1973 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - President, trips, 1961-1970 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - President, trips, Bologna meeting, 1971 (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - Brazil, 1968-1969 (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - California, 1969 (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - Europe, 1968 (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - Europe, 1973 (Box 59, Folder 7)
  - Israel, 1969 (Box 59, Folder 8)
  - Lagos, 1969-1970 (Box 59, Folder 9)
  - Spain, 1964-1965 (Box 59, Folder 10)
  - Provost, 1967 (Box 59, Folder 11)
  - Dean of Faculty, Wash Sq Arts & Science, 1972 (Box 59, Folder 12)
  - Secretary and Legal Council, 1970-1971 (Box 59, Folder 13)
  - Senate, 1971 (Box 59, Folder 14)
  - Senate, Mission Statement, 1969 (Box 59, Folder 15)
  - Senate, Committee, 1970 (Box 59, Folder 16)
  - Senate, Ad Hoc Committee on Black study, 1969 (Box 59, Folder 17)
  - Senate, Banners and Shields Committee, 1967 (Box 59, Folder 18)
  - Senate, Committee on Student Particip., 1967-1968 (Box 59, Folder 19)
  - Student Involvement, 1968-1969 (Box 59, Folder 20)
- Series VIII: Governmental Relations, 1910-1972 (Boxes 60-62)
  This series consists of 15 linear inches of materials arranged alphabetically by subject. The series documents the way in which the University communicated with the Federal, State, and City governments. Box 61 contains a telegram sent to President Richard M. Nixon by President Hester urging him to expedite removal of troops and end US involvement in Vietnam.
  - City, 1966-1971 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - City, Office of the Mayor, 1970-1971 (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - City, Office of the Mayor, Cabinet Meetings, 1967 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - City, Office of the Mayor, Cultural Comm., 1966-1967 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - City, Board of Education, Solution Board, 1963-1964 (Box 60, Folder 5)
  - City, Board of Education, Solution Board, 1965-1968 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  - Board of Higher Ed. Citizens Comm Fitness NY, 1910-1970 (Box 60, Folder 7)
  - City Community Planning Board, 1966-1968 (Box 60, Folder 8)
  - City, Volunteer Coordinating Council, 1969-1970 (Box 60, Folder 9)
  - City, NYC Cultural Council, Theatre studies, 1970-1972 (Box 60, Folder 10)
  - Federal, 1967-1970 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Federal, Pres. of the United States, 1970 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Federal, Response to Nixon telegram, 1970 (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Federal, Response to Nixon telegram, 1970 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - Federal, Departments and Agencies, 1969 (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - Health, education, & welfare, 1968-1971 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - Federal Financing of Higher Educ., 1971-1972 (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - Federal, Health, Education, & Welfare Adv Co, 1968-1969 (Box 61, Folder 8)
  - Federal, Dept. & Agencies, Dept of Defense, 1970-1971 (Box 61, Folder 9)
  - Federal, National Institute of Health, 1970-1972 (Box 61, Folder 10)
  - Federal, Selective Service, 1967-1969 (Box 61, Folder 11)
  - Federal, Selective Service, 1969-1971 (Box 61, Folder 12)
  - Federal, Upward Bound, 1966-1970 (Box 61, Folder 13)
  - Federal, Advisory Comm for Instutional Prog., 1970 (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - Federal, Senate, 1967-1969 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - Federal, Jnt mtg Congress, NYU, & Columbia Sen., 1970 (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Federal, Presidents Comm. on Campus unrest, 1970 (Box 62, Folder 4)
  - Federal, Higher Ed Advisory Comm Wages (Box 62, Folder 5)
  - State, 1967-1969 (Box 62, Folder 6)
  - State, Constitutional Convention, 1967 (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - State, Constitutional Conv, 1967 (Box 62, Folder 8)
  - State, Constitutional Conv, 1967 (Box 62, Folder 9)
  - State, Engineering Education, 1967-1968 (Box 62, Folder 10)
  - State, Office of the Governor, 1969-1972 (Box 62, Folder 11)
  - State, Bundy Legislation, 1968 (Box 62, Folder 12)
  - State, Campus Conduct Legislation, 1969 (Box 62, Folder 13)
  - State, Engineering Education Program, 1969-1972 (Box 62, Folder 14)
  - Other States, 1969-1972 (Box 62, Folder 15)
- Series IX: Personnel Series, 1969-1975 (Boxes 63-65)
  This Series contains 15 linear inches of materials arranged alphabetically by subject. Information within the series pertains to the University`s personnel. Box 63 contains some folders of search committees while the remainder of the collection deals with the unionization efforts of the staff and a strike.
  - Employment Applications, faculty & admin., 1974-1975 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - Employment Applications, Dean WSC, 1970-1972 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Search Committees, 1973-1974 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - School of Law, 1974-1975 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Dentistry, 1974 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - Dentistry, 1974-1975 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Social Work, 1974-1975 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - Wage Freeze, 1971-1975 (Box 63, Folder 8)
  - Tenure, 1974-1975 (Box 63, Folder 9)
  - Union Activities, 1970 (Box 63, Folder 10)
  - Union Activities, Faculty, 1970-1971 (Box 63, Folder 11)
  - Union Activities, Faculty, 1972 (Box 63, Folder 12)
  - Union Activities, Faculty, 1972 (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - Union Activities, Faculty, 1973 (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - Union Activities, Faculty, 1973 (Box 64, Folder 3)
  - Union Activities, Faculty, 1973 (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - Union Activities, Faculty, 1974 (Box 64, Folder 5)
  - Union Activities, Faculty, 1975 (Box 64, Folder 6)
  - NYU's brief concerning Faculty Unionization, undated (Box 64, Folder 7)
  - Staff,Union Organizing-District65vsLocal153, 1970-1971 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - University Statements, District 65, 1969-1971 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Union Statements re District 65, 1970-1971 (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Public Response, 1971 (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - Local 810 Strike, 1971 (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - University Statements, 1970-1971 (Box 65, Folder 6)
  - Union Statements, 1970-1971 (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - Public Response, 1971 (Box 65, Folder 8)
  - S - Z, 1972-1975 (Box 65, Folder 9)
  - Employees, past and present, 1969-1971 (Box 65, Folder 10)
  - Retirement, 1972-1975 (Box 65, Folder 11)
  - Faculty, Staff Benefits, 1973-1975 (Box 65, Folder 12)
- Series X: Public Relations, 1962-1975 (Boxes 65-67)
  This series contains 15 linear inches of materials of information on community relations and public occasions as well as invitations to university events.
  - Public Relations, 1966-1972 (Box 65, Folder 13)
  - Community Relations, 1967-1970 (Box 65, Folder 14)
  - Fordham Redevelopment Commission, 1967-1969 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Washington Square Center, 1966-1967 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Washington Square Center, 1969-1970 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Public Occasions, 1972-1973 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - Public Occasions, 1972-1973 (Box 66, Folder 5)
  - Publications, University, 1971 (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - Publications, non-university, 1970 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - Special Projects, series on Impressionism, 1970-1972 (Box 66, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence about Speeches, Speech Drafts [Not Used], 1962-1972 (Box 66, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence about Speeches, Speech Drafts [Used], 1962-1972 (Box 66, Folder 10)
  - Visits and Visitors, 1972-1975 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - Invitations, NYU, A-E, 1968-1974 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - Invitations, NYU, E-Z, 1968-1975 (Box 67, Folder 3)
- Series XI: Schools and Divisions, 1966-1975 (Boxes 67-69)
  This series contains 6 linear inches of materials arranged alphabetically by school. There are files for each school and division, which contain general information. Box 69 contains files on the Law School, the Law School Foundation, and the C.F. Mueller Company which was owned by the Law School Foundation.
  - Arts, School of, 1972 (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - Arts & Science, Graduate School, Brazilian Inst, 1973 (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - Arts & Science, Graduate School, Brazilian Inst, 1971-1973 (Box 67, Folder 6)
  - Arts & Science, Univ Coll, Univ Computing Cent., 1967-1969 (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - Arts and Science, Wash Sq Coll, 1971-1972 (Box 67, Folder 8)
  - Arts and Science, Wash Sq Coll, Sunrise Semest., 1971 (Box 67, Folder 9)
  - Business, School of, 1974 (Box 67, Folder 10)
  - Business, Schools of: Interim Enrollment Report, 1973 December (Box 69, Folder 14)
  - Business Administration, Grad School of, 1971-1972 (Box 67, Folder 11)
  - Business & Public Adm, Presidents Advisory Co, 1972 (Box 67, Folder 12)
  - Continuing Education, School of, 1973-1974 (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences, 1972-1975 (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - Dentistry, College of, 1973-1975 (Box 68, Folder 3)
  - Dentistry, Accredidation, 1973-1975 (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - Dentistry, NY State/Dental Education, 1972-1975 (Box 68, Folder 5)
  - Education, School of, 1972 (Box 68, Folder 6)
  - Engineering & Science, School of, 1971-1972 (Box 68, Folder 7)
  - International Studies, Center for, 1972 (Box 68, Folder 8)
  - Fine Arts, Institute of, Board of Trustees, 1973-1975 (Box 68, Folder 9)
  - Law, School of, 1971 (Box 68, Folder 10)
  - Dean Evaluations, 1971-1972 (Box 68, Folder 11)
  - Medical Center, 1972 (Box 68, Folder 12)
  - Law, School of - Law Center Foundation, 1972-1974 (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - Law, School of - Law Center Foundation, 1974-1975 (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - Law, School of - C.F. Mueller Company, 1966-1975 (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center, Medicine, School of, 1971-1972 (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center, Medicine, School of, 1974-1975 (Box 69, Folder 5)
  - All-University Departments, 1972 (Box 69, Folder 6)
  - Economics, 1974 (Box 69, Folder 7)
  - Urban Affairs, 1968-1969 (Box 69, Folder 8)
  - Urban Affairs, 1968-1971 (Box 69, Folder 9)
  - WSU, College of Arts and Science, 1972-1975 (Box 69, Folder 10)
  - Arts and Science, Faculty of, 1973-1974 (Box 69, Folder 11)
  - Center for Inter-Disciplinary Programs, 1974-1975 (Box 69, Folder 12)
  - Junior Year in NY, 1974 (Box 69, Folder 13)
- Series XII: Student Affairs Series, 1962-1975 (Boxes 70-79)
  The student affairs series consists of 25 linear inches of material arranged alphabetically into 5 boxes. Within most folders, material is arranged chronologically. This material relates to all student activities including admissions, athletics, campus disorders, clubs, associations, financial aid, dormitory regulations, placement, student publications, centers, and conduct. The bulk of the material in this series relates to the hiring and firing of John F. Hatchett, the director of the Martin Luther King Center for Afro-American Studies.
  The material on Hatchett begins in Box 1, folder 4 and continues until Box 5, folder 6. Briefly, the controversy began when the University attempted to reintegrate the Martin Luther King Jr. Afro-American Student Center into NYU. The Center asked the University to hire Hatchett as director of the Center. Hatchett had been dismissed as a school teacher when he took his students to a Malcolm X memorial service despite an explicit order from the school system not to do so. According to the correspondence from the President's office and memos on the subject, the University was unaware when it hired Hatchett that he had published an article accusing Jewish school teachers of being unable to teach black school children. This article was viewed as anti-Semitic by the Jewish community. When President Hester became aware of this controversy, he discussed the problem with Hatchett and determined that Hatchett was not anti-Semitic. The University defended its decision to hire Hatchett in an internal memo sent to alumni and faculty. Many of the alumni responded with threats to discontinue financial contributions to the University. Since many of the alumni were Jewish and the University was suffering a financial crisis, this threat was taken seriously. Hatchett then made a speech accusing Richard Nixon, then Vice President Hubert Humphrey, and Albert Shanker of being "racist bastards." This remark prompted the University to fire Hatchett. A controversy remained over whether Hatchett was actually fired over this comment or because he had been such an embarrassment from the beginning that the University was looking for an excuse. The letters regarding the Hatchett controversy are filed alphabetically instead of chronologically because that is the way they were received.